web development you've heard about it
you know you have to do it how much of
it do you actually have to learn so if
you take a look at skill. we're now on
uh the week where we are going to talk
about web development so weeks 21
through 25 we're going to spend about
four weeks uh making videos and talking
about website development just a
reminder every day at 9:00 a.m. my time
there's a coffee boost can come on in
and ask your questions you can also ask
in Discord um so as we kick off the web
stage of the beginner boost um just know
that you can come in and get those
questions answered so what does the web
mean let let's let me give you one last
breakdown this is what we're currently
planning uh for the basic uh website
stage uh one well let me just go ahead
and read it this stage lifts you off the
ground by learning the most rudimentary
Tech skills required by any Tech
professional basic web development of
course not everyone will become a web
developer by profession but every single
technologist there's a typo there which
I will now correct there should be an N
there uh is implicitly expected to know
and create simple static web pages with
markdown HTML CSS and perhaps a little
Json and yaml structure data this skill
is so ubiquitous it is almost never
mentioned explicitly any job description
but it is always implied and I really
want to emphasize this this every single
Tech job expects you to know how to make
a web
document they don't expect you how to
make an app or no react but they expect
you to be able to take any kind of
document and just you create
documentation and to write it and you'd
be surprised where this stuff pops up uh
for example in use of slack a lot of
people don't know that slack you know
slack chat which is used a lot of places
or a lot of chat tools they use markdown
and you're like well why markdown so
here's the breakdown of what we're going
to do for now this video might be
changed over time but this is the the
plan for the next four weeks the topics
we're going to cover and I'm going to
make as many of these videos right now
so the first thing we're going to do is
understand why learning basic web
development even matters I kind of
already said it but we'll say it again
know a bit of history about how the web
came to be you might not need to know
the the entire thing but it is actually
extremely interesting to find out how
the web came to be it's I really
encourage you to not skip that video
it's very fun um explain the different
uses of the web some of the biggest
sources of confusion when it comes to
web development come from the inability
for the person to distinguish between
what they're doing on the web okay so
why why and some of the biggest fights
are about completely different types of
web development so we need to talk about
that looking up documentation about web
development when needed we need to know
where to go to get the documentation
where are you going to search you know
is it going to be stack exchange uh you
know spoiler alert we're going to use
the official documentation you need to
learn basic conventional GitHub flavored
markdown that title is very very
specifically chosen because it is so
important that you learn to use
everything
that has been added to markdown from its
original form uh so that you can create
really relevant amazing documents in
fact this the skills. iio site uses that
exact thing and you'll see that most of
the time when you're writing you're
going to be writing in markdown not HTML
but you do need to understand HTML in
order to know how it corresponds to
markdown this is very specific we do not
need to learn more markdown than is I
mean more HTML than is required we will
look at the HTML specification and it
can be somewhat overwhelming because
there's so much stuff there you're going
to be like do I need to learn every
single one of these answers no but you
should learn enough HTML so that you can
at least understand a markdown document
that's been converted into a document
notice I keep saying document right this
is super important I'm not saying app
right I'm saying document and that's
because this create a basic
website uh is fundamentally about
documents and we talk about in that in
the different uses of the web video so
next learn just enough CSS to style a
basic website you want to change your
background you want to you know maybe
create a well that's really
it you just want to stylize your website
you don't want to make it too crazy um
that's what CSS is for you want to
change your fonts uh you know we are not
going to get into all the crazy things
you can do with CSS um CSS is
actually we'll talk about it when we get
there but CSS is itself has become
something of a programming language
almost it's not really but there are
there are web designers who are very
proud of the fact that they've done
incredible things including animating
X-Wing you know flying across the screen
in CSS with no coding whatsoever with no
JavaScript okay and and actually I want
you to show show you this you'll notice
there is no JavaScript here and I want
you to take note of that right web
design fundamentally doesn't necessarily
have JavaScript in it and uh learning
web design is a very famous book it does
have a little SE segment in it that's in
JavaScript and that segment that about
JavaScript has actually been written by
somebody else because the author doesn't
consider that an important thing and
when you're creating web sites and not
web applications
uh they are primarily composed of mostly
static meaning not changing elements of
HTML and CSS most of the time that have
been derived from markdown and so there
is no JavaScript in fact when you when
it comes to vanilla JavaScript that
comes on the scene when you kind of want
to do things that get triggered by other
things well CSS has covered most of that
right we are not going to get deep into
CSS but we are going to learn enough
basic CSS so that you can you can
understand what your page looks like um
I think something one last thing is
really important that I note that's not
going to be here there is not going to
be anything about creating interactive
forms uh or submissions or um you know
we we do that in JavaScript but we do
like an interactive Story game but none
of that interactivity with a website is
included in this stage we are going to
do programming very you know JavaScript
programming Python Programming and go
programming at the same time in a
different stage so lest anybody panic in
the code stage which is not for a while
we will be learning to code in three
languages at the same time we're going
to be learning JavaScript we're going to
be learning Python and we're going to be
learning go at the same time and it's
very important that I say vanilla
JavaScript right we're going to be
learning those three programming
languages at the same time from a very
basic perspective in other words just
enough to help you understand what
coding is about we're not going to be
doing any lead code or any of that so so
just know that that's coming uh so
where's the JavaScript so that's the
answer to that structure data so along
with um building a website a lot of
times people don't realize that you have
to have data in fact data driven
websites are the most powerful and so
will be learning to structure data into
Json and yaml and we'll learn what that
means what does structure data look like
um to give you a sense of this really
quickly if you go to RBX
Rob uh sorry github.com RBX Rob uh
Rob Rob SL CV you can see um the idea
here so here is data. yl uh this is my
this is what structured data looks like
and as you can probably guess structured
data is much more easy to maintain and
by keeping data in a structured format
uh earlier early in your career as you
go through this kind of stuff you'll
find that there are many opportunities
for you to use structured data as a sort
of database we we're not going to do
databases at all during the beginner
boost but um most structured data is a
database to some degree right a place to
put put data that you can be then
queried um for our purposes though
static structured data Json and yaml uh
in particular I made the toml logo by
the way if you know toml um that this
structured data is for use and capturing
you know some very structured data about
a thing so I used to use structured data
uh uh for my school I you know I had all
my students were in there uh did I have
to implement an entire postgress
database or whatever no I didn't I just
maintain these static structured data
files so it's super important that when
you're learning about writing documents
on the web that those documents include
structured data which can then be
converted into you know non-structured
data or markup data with markup that can
then be SE seen in a web page as is the
case for this um little thing here let
me actually one last thing so if you
wanted to see what what this is we are
going to make this this kind of a nice
leadin so I did make a resumé rendering
of this and we will learn a little bit
of of something but here's the PDF this
PDF was actually generated from that
structured data and as you can see you
can use sorry for the flashbang there
you can use structured data to do a lot
of amazing things and we are going to
begin using structure data to start
working on your rum and your CV on
GitHub and by doing that you'll
automatically be able to say that you've
had experience with Json yaml writing
structure data and um will'll also be
ready to do some of the coding later on
to turn that structured data into a
static website either as or as a PDF or
however you want to do it so that you
can then show that you've done something
right so one of your first Web projects
your first apps in your portfolio will
be your resum or your CV and you can
actually provide a link to it that way
um and you the thing is really great
about it is you can go in and change it
and then you can render it so you can
actually have it be uh tailored to a
specific job so if you want to get like
a backend uh systems developer job like
I have right now or you want to do it
infrastructure even though you have
experience there you can you can create
a different resum depending on that from
the same structured data and you have an
app an app you know you have experience
with coding to show that you've got at
least that level and I I feel like
that's a really relevant project right
off the bat for everybody everybody
needs to have something like that so
this has been a long video but this is
the overview video of what we're going
to be covering during the creative basic
website stage so stay tuned and follow
along with the other videos again if you
have questions come join us on the
beginner boost or during in the copy
boost or in the Discord